<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Ostend of, the oppugnation, and fierce siege made, by the Archeduke Albertus his forces, commanded by the Duke of Ossuna who came before the saide towne, the fift day of Iulie last past (after their writing) 1601. Shewing what hath hapned since the time of the saide siege. Now newly imprinted; whereunto are aded such other newes and accidents as haue lately hapned at Ostend, as we haue bin certainely informed. Diligently translated out of Dutch into English, according to the Dutch copie, printed at Amsterdam.</title>
            <title>Oppugnation, and fierce siege of Ostend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18893</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848095</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13173</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13173)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1637:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Ostend of, the oppugnation, and fierce siege made, by the Archeduke Albertus his forces, commanded by the Duke of Ossuna who came before the saide towne, the fift day of Iulie last past (after their writing) 1601. Shewing what hath hapned since the time of the saide siege. Now newly imprinted; whereunto are aded such other newes and accidents as haue lately hapned at Ostend, as we haue bin certainely informed. Diligently translated out of Dutch into English, according to the Dutch copie, printed at Amsterdam.</title>
                  <title>Oppugnation, and fierce siege of Ostend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by V. S[immes] for Thomas Pauier, and are to be sold at his shop in Cornehill, at the signe of the Catte and two Parrots,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Text begins on A1v.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>A reimposition of: The oppugnation, and fierce siege of Ostend.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ostend (Belgium) --  History --  Siege, 1601-1604 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1604 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13173:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newes from Oſtend, of, The Oppugnation, and fierce ſiege, <hi>made, by the Archeduke</hi> Albertus his Forces, commanded by the Duke of Oſſuna who came before the ſaide Towne, the fift day of Iulie laſt paſt (after their writing) 1601. ſhewing what hath hapned ſince the time of the ſaide ſiege.</p>
            <p>Now newly imprinted; whereunto are added ſuch other Newes and Accidents as haue lately hapned at Oſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, as we haue bin certainely informed.</p>
            <p>Diligently tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Dutch Copie, Printed at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by V.S. for Thomas Pauier, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Cornehill, at the ſigne of the Cat and two Parrots. 1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Oppugnation and fierce ſiege of Oſtend, <hi>by the Arch-duke</hi> Albertus his Forces, commanded by the Duke of Oſſuna, who came before the ſaid Towne, the fift day of Iuly laſt paſt (after their writing) 1601. ſhewing what hath hapned ſince the time of the ſaide ſiege.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Stend</hi> is a towne ſcituated on the Flemiſh coaſt, lying on the arme of the riuer <hi>Y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le,</hi> thorowe which the weaſt Sluice lately ranne into the ſea, and hath there made a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tide hauen, which (like as, for the moſt parte, al the reſt of the Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh hauens, doe ebbe and flowe: and cannot be vſed but with an high water, or at the leaſt wiſe, at halfe flood) doth notwithſtanding conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually holde, and containe the ditches of the Towne full of water, by reaſon of Dammes and Sluces made to that end and purpoſe, which (foraſmuch as it might be in the ſame courſe continued, returned, or perhappes by the ennemy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted) they of the Towne haue, of themſelues, ſtopped the courſe thereof, whereby they of the Country of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> haue héene forced to carry and conuey the ſame by the Forte of <hi>Albertus,</hi> and ſo by a new currant into the Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13173:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
In times paſt, it was but an open village, yet reaſonable great, and well peopled. Firſt, after the comming of <hi>Don Iohn d'Auſtria,</hi> in the beginning of the nowe warres, for the fitte and commodious ſcituation thereof, it was made a Towne, and enuironed with ſtrong walles: And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, this Towne only, and none others among all the reſt of the ſea townes of <hi>Flaunders</hi> remayned, and at this preſent doth remayne in the poſſeſſion or amitie of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prouinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> howbeit, it lieth in the middle (as it were) of the ennemies Countrie, and farre from her friendes. And yet maugre all the forces, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of her enuirouing foes, hath many times béene valiantly defended againſt ſundry beſiegings and attempts.</p>
            <p>For in the yéere <hi>1583.</hi> although the duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> with his victorious hoſte (after he had taken <hi>Dunkerk,</hi> and <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> the next adioyning ſea Townes weſtward) didde in moſt furious maner beſiege it, vſing all warlike meanes hée coulde poſſible to conquer it, was forced to giue place, and after that he had continued his ſiege fiue dayes, ſawe how booteleſſe it was for him to ſpend any longer time about it, and therefore departed, not effecting any thing agréeable to his wiſhed attempts.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes, in the yeere <hi>1585.</hi> although <hi>Monſieur la Motte</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Graueling,</hi> did, with great force and difficultie winne the olde Towne by the Strand or ſea ſide, which at that time was onely defended with a ſimple wall, or <hi>Raueling</hi> and <hi>Palliſados,</hi> with purpoſe there preſently to intrench and defend himſelfe, was againe with all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, like ſhéepe driuen out of the ſame, leauing behind him fortie of his principalleſt Captaynes and Commaunders with all their furniture and prouiſion.</p>
            <p>This Towne, without all queſtion, is a place of great aduantage, and importaunce, yea of ſuch moment, that it ſerueth as a bulwarke and ſtrong defence, for the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Zeland,</hi> and ſo contrariwiſe, if it ſhoulde fall into
<pb facs="tcp:13173:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the enomies hands (as God forbid) he ſhould thereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund a more fitte and commodious hauen for ſhipping, than any other ſea Towne nowe in his poſſeſſion can yeelde him. Yea our intollerable loſſes, not to be recouered doe teach vs, and as it were, with a finger poynt vnto vs, what ineſtimable domage might redound vnto the vnited Prouinces, if the enemy ſhould commaund in this Town.</p>
            <p>Further, it is to be noted, that the Country of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> beeing in peace, in all taxations of the ſeauenteene Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did leuy the third peny: whereunto they haue béene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by this Towne, not only during the time of theſe wars, but alſo, the greateſt part of the maine land hath béene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained many yéeres, to pay toll and contribution, and to be vnder our deuotion.</p>
            <p>For which cauſes, this Towne hath with great care and mighty charges of the vnited Prouinces bin daily fortified, and continually ſtrengthned, and eſpecially in the yéere laſt paſt <hi>1600.</hi> as alſo in the fore parte of this preſent ſummer: many workes, I ſay, haue béene deuiſed to withſtand, and preuent the cruell attempts of the bloody ennemy, as bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, counterpoynts, and Rauelings to the landward, neither hath that part lying to the Sea béene forgotten, but hath béene made alſo very defencible with heades, bankes, and ditches, and eſpecially on the eaſt ſide of the Towne where (by meanes of the weakeneſſe of the bankes) the ſea, with great force is mightily broken into the land, where it hath ſkowred, and pierced a great depth; ſo that the chanel of the new hauen (when the water is loweſt) is neere twoo, pikes déepe: and doth daily waxe déeper and déeper, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, the determinate worke of God, for the great ſtrengthning and playne defence of the Towne.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Flaunders</hi> generally finding what annoyaunnes and great diſcommoditie this Towne threatned daily vnto them, haue ſolicited and by all meanes poſſible importuned their Gouernours, to beſiege, and conquer this Towne of
<pb facs="tcp:13173:3"/>
               <hi>Oſtend,</hi> their daily eie-ſore: as of late yéeres (yet freſh in memorie) in the yeare <hi>1596.</hi> after that the Archduke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> had taken the Towne of <hi>Callice,</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> they required him then to take in hand this péece of worke, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to giue him twelue hundred thouſand gilderns with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three moneths time (which in ſterling money is one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty thouſand poundes) wherevnto, after his Highneſſe had made ſhew to yéelde, and promiſed to fulfil their deſire, he gote ſome parte of the ſumme aforeſayde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his handes. But doubting the euent of the attempt, or knowing howe hard a matter it was, to take it by force of armes, or how difficult it woulde be to conſtraine the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof by hunger, or otherwiſe, thought it ſufficient to ſhew himſelfe before the Towne with his forces, and ſo qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly to departe.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Flaunders</hi> herewith nothing at all pleaſed, and gréeued with the continuall vexations and incurſions of the ranging ſouldiers, and payment of contributions, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the ſame, in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1599.</hi> while our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were imployed in the defence of <hi>Bommel,</hi> had good ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to make ſundry forts and bulwarkes, for the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; defence of the wayes and paſſages about the towne of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> thereby (as it were with a ſmall kinde of ſiege) continually to trouble the Towne, and to hinder the incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the gariſon: which deuice was put into their heads, and the plotte layde downe by a certaine Corporall of the Towne called <hi>Noel,</hi> who hauing before long ſerued in the towne, and hauing good experience of the ſecrets thereof, vppon ſome diſcontentment receiued, forſooke the Towne, and ran to the ſeruice of the enemy.</p>
            <p>But as the experience of the laſt yeare giueth ſufficient proofe, that all the ſtrength of theſe Fortes is not able to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or defend the entrance of an Hoſte, ſo alſo it is moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that by the continuall charge of the Garriſons of theſe Fortes, the Country hath receiued more domage and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoditie,
<pb facs="tcp:13173:4"/>then before it did by the contribution to their enemies, and Towne of <hi>Oſtend;</hi> wherefore they haue been forced to renewe their Importunate ſute vnto his Highnes, and to ſollicit him againe to the beſieging of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially at this inſtant, knowing our forces to be remoued farre from them, and to be ſent into Dutchland lying at the ſiege of <hi>Berck,</hi> where they ſhould (as they imagined) haue long worke: And for the better perſwading, and more eaſily drawing of the Archduke to harken to this their ſute, haue promiſed to pay him extraordinarily, thrée hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand gilderns Monthly (which is <hi>30</hi> thouſand pounds ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) during the time of the ſiege, and after the taking of the towne to pay him farther (for the ſpace of two years) ninety thouſand gilderns euery month (which is <hi>9000.</hi> 
               <abbr>l</abbr> ſtarling.</p>
            <p>Hereupon tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rchduke gathred together al his ſouldiers: yea ſuch as were about the riuer of <hi>Ryne</hi> &amp; the <hi>Maſe,</hi> for the ſuccor of <hi>Berck</hi> were ſent for, to make their repaire into <hi>Flaunders</hi> and to ſerue vnder the commaund of the Duke of <hi>Oſluna,</hi> who not long ſince was to that end ſent for out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> by reaſon that the Archdukes campe (thorow the long impriſonment of the <hi>Adinirant</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and the laſt ouerthrowe in <hi>Flaunders</hi>) was wholy left deſtitute and vnprouided of a ſufficient Commaunder, and experient Leaders, and for that the naturall Lordes of the land, are in no wiſe reſpected nor truſted.</p>
            <p>VPon the ſift day of Iune (after the new ſtile) the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> about noone, with eight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of footmen, which were eight thouſand men ſtrong, deſides the horſemen (notwithſtanding the Spaniards ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally diſliked of this enterpriſe, and counſelled the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who (as is reported) do wholly diſlike of this ſiege: and among the reſt, twoo common ſouldiers that hadde béene the laſt yeare priſoners in <hi>Oſtend,</hi> obſtinately maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the invincible ſtrength of this Towne, were preſently
<pb facs="tcp:13173:4"/>taken and hanged: for the extreame want of the thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand gilderns, to be payed monthly, as before is ſaide, comming very fitly for the payment of the mutined ſouldiers, and alſo the hope to drawe our forces from the ſiege of <hi>Bercke,</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> for the better furniſhing of him ſelfe, &amp; preuenting of ſuch wants as might happen to <hi>Oſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end:</hi> and perhaps thinking ſodainly, and with al his force to ouercharge the towne before it ſhould be ſuccored, haue bin the reſons to bring th Archdukes forces now before <hi>Oſtend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Oſſuna</hi> preſently ſought to paciſie the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of <hi>Iſſabella,</hi> which had before mutined for their pay: and the next day folowing, being the fixt day of Iuly, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſix péeces of ordonance againſt the eaſt ſide of the towne vpon the Downes, and with the ſame beganne fiercely to play vpon the Towne.</p>
            <p>There were then in the towne in garriſon one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ancients of ſundry Regiments, and one company of Burgers, or Towneſmen, all vnder the direction and commaund of Captayne <hi>Vander Noote.</hi> Theſe preſently prepared themſelues to their defence, making harmeleſſe, and diſplacing ſome of the enemies artillerie: And labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, to make a new way or hauen, betwéene the heads, to the end the paſſage of boates and ſhipping might be frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ordonaunce of the ennemy.</p>
            <p>And the ninth day of Iuly, after that they had ſent away the moſt parte of their wiues and children, they receiued into the towne (out of <hi>Zeland</hi>) <hi>28.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies of ſouldiers, with great abundance of victuals, and all other prouiſion of war.</p>
            <p>The tenth day ſir <hi>Frances Vere,</hi> with eight companies of Engliſhmen entred into the Towne alſo, who preſently iſſued out of the Towne with his people, entrenching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on the drie plottes of ground next vnto the walles, on the weſt ſide, from whence the enemy might haue endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged the towne, and battered the walles.</p>
            <p>The thirtéenth day of Iuly, the ſayde ſir <hi>Frances Vere,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:13173:5"/>with great force and reſolution ſallied vpon the enemy with eight hundred men, on the weſt parte of the towne, and ſet vpon the Campe, which lay farre off diuided from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with waters and mariſh grounds, and can not eaſily, or in ſhort time come to ayde each other. In which ſally, the ennemy loſt (as was certified by Letters from <hi>Antwerpe</hi>) aboue eight hundred men, and among the ſame, one cornet of horſemen: and, if the whole force of the ennemies horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, had not the ſóoner come to their ayde, it was moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to all mens iudgements, that ſir <hi>Frances</hi> had dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the footemen to great confuſion, and taken from them their Ordonance.</p>
            <p>The fiue and twentieth day ſir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> did agayne iſſue out of the Towne with fifteene hundred men, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to intrench betwéene <hi>Iſſabella</hi> and <hi>Grootendorſt,</hi> on a high ground, which in times paſt was an old Churchyard, where they of <hi>Iſſabella</hi> and <hi>Grootendorſt</hi> were accuſtomed to bury their dead, and is a very fitte and apt place, to ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and cutte off theſe two Fortes from each others helpe, and to open a faire way to thoſe of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> to the flatte and plaine land. To which place of buriall, the next day, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fiue and twentieth day of Iuly, the ennemy came with thrée thouſand men, and after hée had béene thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed, and put to the woorſt, tooke the place, but was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently with great force and dexteritie driuen from it agayne.</p>
            <p>The ſame day tenne companies of ſouldiers arriued at <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and were receiued into the Towne, which were ſent thither by her Maieſtie from <hi>London,</hi> ſo that now the Towne was furniſhed (within the walles and without) with ſixtie and ſeauen companies, which made vp neere the number of ſeuen thouſand men: theſe tenne companies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, were preſently employed againſt the enemy, who ſhewed themſelves very valorous, and did, both then, and ſince, paſſing good ſeruice, although many men were of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that they would prooue vnſitte for any ſeruice by
<pb facs="tcp:13173:5"/>reaſon they were rawe, and had not béene trayned.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the Arch duke daily ſtrengtheneth and encreaſeth his Campe, as well with ſouldiers, as with ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, playing continually on the weſt ſide with <hi>26.</hi> péeces, and on the eaſt ſide with nine péeces of ordonance, but moſt of his ſhotte liteth vppon the houſes, whereof many are defaced and beaten downe: For, this ſixe and twentieth day of Iuly, and before, there had beene diſcharged vppon the Towne ſixtéene thouſand ſhot, and againſt the ennemie from the Towne had béene counterchanged ſix thouſand.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there were alſo receiued into the Campe ſome parte of the new ſouldiers which came out of <hi>Italie,</hi> and had béene appoynted for the ſuccour of <hi>Berke,</hi> for firſt there arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eight hundred men of thoſe companies, and afterwards fiue and twenty hundred more were ſent for, part Italians, and part Spaniards: and beſides theſe, xx. men more out of all the other Ancients vnder the gouernment of the Erie of <hi>Barlamont</hi> and <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> who, for this cauſe, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to diſcharge their wagons, and other prouiſions, before by them taken vp, and meant to be vſed in raiſing the ſiege before <hi>Bercke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are eightéene companies appoynted euery night out of the Towne, to garde ſir <hi>Frances Veres</hi> trenches on the ſouth weſt parte of the Towne, who daily falleth out vppon the ennemy, with other ſouldiers of the Towne, and haue oftentimes ſlayne many of the ennemies, &amp; wounded more, which haue béene ſent to <hi>Bruges</hi> from the Campe, ſo that their Hoſpitalles are full of wounded ſouldiers, and many Captaines, and men of great accompt, aſwell Spaniardes, Italians, and others, haue béene ſlaine in theſe conflictes, and amongeſt the reſt, a Colonell of the Spaniardes was brought to <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> and there firſt buryed in his armour, and afterwardes taken vp againe, and put into the earth in a Friars wéede, with great ſolempnitie.</p>
            <p>On Sonday, being the ſixe and twentieth day of Iuly
<pb facs="tcp:13173:6"/>laſt paſt, was a great ſkirmiſh with the ennemy, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued very long, and was with great furie, valour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution maintained on both ſides, the ennemy ſupplying his ſouldiers with freſh companies, bringing thrée, foure, and fiue companies at a time, and they of the Towne ſeconding their parte continually with newe ſupplies, and with like numbers, ſo that in the end, it ſeemed rather a little battell, than a ſkirmiſh, ſometime our people being ouermatched with the freſh companies of their ennemies, were forced to giue ground: but preſently againe, with their new ſupplies from the Towne, couragiouſly preſſed into the thickeſt of the enimies, making them likewiſe to retire into their trenches: and thus it continued long, ſometimes the one parte, and ſometimes the other giuing ground, vntill the ennemies horſemen came in, to ſuccour their footemen, wherevppon our men returned into their trenches, and into the Towne, after they had ſlaine and ſpoiled many of their enemies both horſe and foote. But if our men had béene furniſhed with horſemen, the ennemy had loſt many more men than hée did, both in this ſkirmiſh, and all others before: but héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the enemy hath had the vantage of vs during this ſiege, notwithſtanding it hath béene written from <hi>Callice,</hi> that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this fight, there were carried out of the Campe to <hi>Bruges</hi> thrée ſcore and ten wagons laden with wounded men, and in euery wagon was tenne men at the leaſt: but when they were brought to <hi>Bruges,</hi> they of the Towne woulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, ſaying that they had their Hoſpitalles alreadie full, and coulde receiue no more, and therefore required that they might be conueyed to ſome other townes. It was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes reported, that the ennemy loſt in this ſhirmiſh <hi>450.</hi> men, beſides thoſe that were wounded: neyther was this attempt accompliſhed, without loſſe on our ſide.</p>
            <p>Saterday, being the firſt day of this preſent moneth of Auguſt, they of the Towne iſſued againe vpon the ennemy, and with great furie (after they had continued ſkirmiſh ſom
<pb facs="tcp:13173:6"/>halfe houre) forced them to retire to their trenches, ſlaying ſome <hi>80.</hi> of their enemies, as néere as could be iudged: but the horſemen of the enemy comming in vpon our ſouldiers, they returned into the Towne, with ſmall loſſe on our part.</p>
            <p>It is reported by ſome that came very lately from <hi>Callice,</hi> that on wedneſday laſt, being the fift day of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Auguſt, there was a great Skirmiſh begunne by thoſe of the Towne, to hinder the enemies approach vnto the walles, which was with fierce reſolution long continued on both ſides, and that they of the towne (with great ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their enemies) had taken thrée or fiue péeces of ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and brought the ſame into the Towne, but how cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this is (being but a reporte) I cannot write, the trueth thereof will he hereafter better knowne.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> without the Towne doth daily fortify his trenches: and the Gouernour within the Towne, with earth raiſeth the walles, thereby to auoyde the daunger of the enemies ſhot, which his Highneſſe ſpareth not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth ſo liberally vpon the Towne, as if he found ſhot and powder aboundauntly in the Downes, or ſand-hilles: and withall, laboreth to raiſe a new Cauallirie, with bauen and earth, thereon ſo plant more ordonaunce, and to ſhoote in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Towne, on the ſouth ſouthweſt ſide. Thus they are earneſtly buſied on all ſides, the one, nor the other ſparing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny coſt or labor to annoy their enemy, and to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and that thing which to day is not thought vpon, is the next day put in practiſe, with new deuiſes and warlike ſtratagems, the one raiſing vp, the other with his ordonance beating downe his ennemies works, that the ſame may not be finiſhed, or brought to perfection.</p>
            <p>It is alſo written from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> that the <hi>Infanta</hi> is in perſon come into the Campe, and that the Archduke is in <hi>Ondenburgh,</hi> to the end he may himſelfe in perſon giue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in theſe affaires: time will teach vs to knowe what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite hée ſhal reape by theſe his trauels &amp; ineſtimable charges.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13173:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But at her returne from the Camp to <hi>Bruges,</hi> ſhée broght with her ſundry Companies of Souldiers, but they of the Towne denyed to receiue them, ſaying they had no néede of any new Garriſon, but if it pleaſed her highnes to come into the Towne with her accuſtomed trayne, ſhée ſhould be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: but as for her Souldiers, they were not minded to take them into the Cittie.</p>
            <p>Such as haue come out of <hi>Oſtend</hi> very lately, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> reporte for certaine, that within the Towne of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> there wanteth not any thing, fit for the defence thereof, and that all victualles are very plentifull, Engliſh béere is ſolde for twoo ſtiuars the kanne, great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for which there is no exciſe payde. Sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> giueth the enemie daily ſo much to doe, and kéepeth him ſo well occupied, that he knoweth not well which way to turne him, or what hée may well beginne to annoy the Towne: and it is thought by many men of good iudgement, that hée wiſheth he had not come to beſiege <hi>Oſtend,</hi> ſeeing he findeth ſo ſmall hope to carry it, but would rather be with his camp from thence, if he knew how with credite to departe.</p>
            <p>Lately the enemy remooued nine péeces of his ordonance, from the eaſt to the weaſt ſide: his ordonance made it verie dangerous to enter by the accuſtomed hauen, except it were in the night time, but ſince the making of the laſt, or middle hauen, all things are carried in and out without any daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the enemies ſhot. And on the ſouthweſt ſide the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my bringeth great ſtore of bruſh and bauen fagots towards the trenches of ſir <hi>Frances Vere,</hi> thinking by that meanes ſo to mount ſome ordonaunce, that hée may beate ſir <hi>Frances</hi> from his trenches, and ſo bring his battering péeces néerer vnto the walles, or elſe, to beate the Towne on the ſouth ſouthweſt ſide.</p>
            <p>On the ſouth ſide, the ennemy hath raiſed a mount, from whence hée beateth the houſes, but ſpecially the Church and Stéeple, which is wholy defaced, otherwiſe, he doeth ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:13173:7"/>annoyance to the Towne, ſometimes with his ſhot killing a man: but ſuch as come out of the Towne affirme, that for euery one the Towne looſeth, the enemy looſeth fiue or ſixe. They of the Towne, haue themſelues, vntiled and taken downe many houſes, and alſo vnpaued the ſtréetes, to ſhend the ſame might with the enemies ſhot, the leſſe annoy them.</p>
            <p>The Gouernor and ſir <hi>Frances</hi> are not ydle, but employ all their labour and induſtrie, both within the Towne and without, to raiſe mounts, and to finiſh ſuch other workes, as are moſt behoouefull for the ſtrengthening of the Towne againſt the enemies forces, and to that end, ſuch ſouldiers as will worke, and employ their time that way, eyther by day or night, haue xii. d. the day, and xii. d. the night.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the enemy ſhall the better be kept from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching the walles, they of the Towne haue cutte the Sea banckes, ſo that the Sea water enuironeth the Towne on the ſouth ſide, from the eaſt to the weaſt parte, in ſo much that the towne ſéemeth to ſtand in an Iland, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth great hurt to the land and countrie thereabouts, and may (in time) growe very daungerous.</p>
            <p>The enemies perceiuing them of the towne to be very ſtil, and thoſe likewiſe of ſir <hi>Frances Veres</hi> trenches to hold them ſelues more quiet than they had bin accuſtomed, ſent out a ſouldier to eſpie their doings: one of the ſouldiers that came from <hi>London</hi> ſpying this ſtragler, demanded of ſuch as wer next him in the trenches, what he meant thus to approache their trenches: it was anſwered, they knew not, except hee came as a ſpie: then quoth the Engliſh ſouldier, I will goe out and talke with him: preſently he made toward this ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, and making but few wordes, they ſell to blowes, and ſo continued a good ſpace, the camp on thone ſide, and the town on thother, beholding them, &amp; noting which did beſt: In the end they were both wounded, and ſo departed: the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man brought with him his enemies hat, and a ſtaffe or halfe pike, which he valiantly won, and broght into the trenches.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13173:8"/>
Since the beſieging of this Towne, the fiue Gallies of <hi>Sluice</hi> were at ſea, and (méeting with twoo ſhips laden with marchandize, which came from <hi>Doit</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> hauing a ſhippe of warre for their conuoy and defence) there began a hote fight on both ſides, and it continued long: the ſhippe of warre beſtowed his ſhot ſo well, that hée did great ſpoyle to the Gallies, and ſlewe many of their men, but in thend, the Gallies boorded the ſhippe, (and firing her) did, without mercie, put ſeauentie ſixe men to the ſworde, and ſaued one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ten perſons, which, for the moſt part, are ſhorn, and made ſlaues. It was reported, that this ſhippe of warre was, by ouerſight, ſet on fire with their owne powder: but by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of <hi>Holland,</hi> it ſéemeth to be otherwiſe, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen from thence, that it pleaſed God to ſaue one man verie myraculouſly, who (committing himſelfe to the mercie of God, and of the mercileſſe Seas, vppon a péece of a Maſte) rather than hée woulde fall into the handes of his bloody en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: after hee had ſo floated vpon the waues of the Sea an houre or twoo, he was taken vp by an other ſhip, which (by Gods prouidence) had ſpyed the man thus driuing on the water. This man (after his comming into <hi>Holland</hi>) made true reporte héereof, as is aboue declared.</p>
            <p>Within the Towne, néere vnto the weſt end, they haue raiſed a mount, whereon is planted twelue cannons, and ſixe demy cannons, wherewith they beate downe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the ennemies workes without.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſuch as came on wedneſday laſt out of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fift day of this preſent moneth of Auguſt, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the former report from <hi>Callice</hi>) affirme that thene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie hath theſe viii. dayes layne ſtil, and doone nothing, and affirme, the ſouldiers of <hi>Oſtend</hi> to be of an inuincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, not eſteeming any force of the enemy, and that there is no cauſe of feare, nor want, for all things are daily in moſt plentifull ſort brought vnto them, aſſuring themſelues, that the ennemy ſhal (in the end) be forced to depart with ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:13173:8"/>and diſhonor, and perhappes with greater loſſe than he now thinks vpon, which God for his mercies ſake grant, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SInce the former Impreſſion of this Pamphlet, wee haue not heard of any to be come from <hi>Oſtend,</hi> neither haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Letters béene receiued from <hi>Zeland.</hi> But from <hi>Callice</hi> it is written, by the Poſte, which came thence with the <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe</hi> Letters, thrée dayes paſt (namely the thirtéenth day of this moneth of Auguſt) that it is generally reported by thoſe that come out of <hi>Flaunders</hi> to <hi>Callice,</hi> that the ennemie beginneth to waxe colde, hopeleſſe in his attempts before <hi>Oſtend:</hi> and all men which are not partiall, iudge al his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt, and his exceſſiue charges to be ſpent in vaine. And further, it is ſayde for certaine, that vpon friday being the ſeuenth day of this moneth of Auguſt, the winde blowing a great gale from the northweſt, brought ſuch plentie of water vpon the Flemiſh coaſt, that the ennemy ſtoode aboue their knees in water, in ſome of their trenches, and that the Sea waſhing and vndermining the foundation of the laſt mount, made by the enemy on the ſouth weſt ſide of the Towne, the ſame ſunke, and is wholy defaced: at what time they of <hi>Oſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> iſſued out, and making great ſlaughter of their enemies, brought one péece of ordonance into the towne. But ſome do report that the enemy loſt then fiue péeces, and that the reſt which lay vpon the ſayd Mount (being foure péeces more) were, by our ſouldiours, ſo choaked and nayled, that in long time the ſame cannot be made agayne ſeruiceable.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, on friday laſt being the fouretéenth day of this preſent moneth of Auguſt, there arriued héere in the <hi>Thames,</hi> twoo ſmall Pinckes which came with fiſh from <hi>Terueare</hi> in <hi>Walkerland,</hi> who report that the twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men (of the number of the laſt two thouſand which were preſſed, and ſent by her Maieſty) are in ſafety arriued at <hi>Vluſhing,</hi> where they as yet remaine, for that in the town of <hi>Oſtend</hi> they haue ſufficient forces, as well to defend the
<pb facs="tcp:13173:9"/>Towne, as to guard their trenches without. And alſo, that the Countie <hi>Maurice</hi> was come into the <hi>Haege</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> moſt of his footemen béeing in <hi>Zeland,</hi> and his horſemen at <hi>Bergen ap Zome,</hi> expecting his comming thither: but, where hee meant to vſe his forces (as good reaſon is) was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. At their comming from <hi>Terueare,</hi> it was general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagined, that they ſhould bée imployed in the land of <hi>Waſte,</hi> which is the moſt fruitfull and fertileſt part of all the Prouince of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and where his Excellency may moſt endomage the enimy. Time will manifeſt the truth, God graunt him good ſucceſſe in all his attempts, and to thoſe of <hi>Oſtend,</hi> courage and magnanimity, valiantly to reſiſt the forces of their bloodthirſty enemies, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13173:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
